A Guide to the Papers of Charles Wright ca. 1890-1998
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence 1967-1998, n.d. (Box 1-21)
  - B: Chonological Correspondence 1970-1998, n.d. (Box 17-21)
    arranged by date
    - Correspondence re Awards 1980-1998 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence--Greeting Cards [ca. 1980-1997] (Box 17)
    - Correspondence re Invitations & Announcements 1982-1998 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence re Invitations to Conferences, Workshops, Poetry Readings, etc. 1970-1998, n.d., 11 folders (Box 18-19)
    - Correspondence re Poetry Magazine Publications and Anthologies 1972-1998, n.d., 6 folders (Box 19-20)
    - Correspondence--Postcards [ca. 1970-1990], 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Correspondence re Requests to Judge Poetry Competitions 1974-1997, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Correspondence re Requests for Recommendations and Evaluations 1983-1998, 5 folders (Box 20-21)
- Manuscripts of Works by Charles Wright 1963-1999, n.d. (Box 21-29)
  - A: Bound Volumes of Poetry & Translation Notebooks kept by Charles Wright 1968-1999 (Box 21-23)
    - Poetry Notebooks, AMsS, containing original poetry by Charles Wright 1968 Nov-1999 Feb, 12 volumes (Box 21-23)
    - Poetry Notebook--Translations, etc., by Charles Wright 1983 Jul-1993 Oct (Box 23)
    - "Halflife (A Commonplace NoteBook)" 1977-1990 (Box 23)
  - B: Poetry Manuscripts Arranged by Title of Book ca. 1968-1994 (Box 24-29)
    - Appalachia Page Proofs, with corrections 1998 Apr (Box 24)
    - Appalachia Page Proofs 1998 Jun (Box 24)
    - Black Zodiac TMs (Setting Copy) 1996 (Box 24)
    - Black Zodiac Page Proofs, with corrections 1996 (Box 24)
    - Black Zodiac Page Proofs (Author's Copy), with corrections ca. 1996 (Box 24)
    - Black Zodiac Page Proofs, Master Pages First Pass 1997 (Box 24)
    - Black Zodiac Master Pages 1997 (Box 24)
    - Chickamauga TMs ca. 1994 (Box 24)
    - Chickamauga TMs (Setting Copy) ca. 1994 (Box 24)
    - Chickamauga TMs 1994 Dec (Box 25)
    - Chickamauga TMs (Setting Copy) 1994 Dec (Box 25)
    - China Trace TMs ca. 1977 (Box 25)
    - Country Music Selected Early Poems TMs ca. 1982 (Box 25)
    - The Grave of the Right Hand and The Dream Animal TMs ca. 1968-1970 (Box 25)
    - Halflife Improvisations and Interviews, 1977-1987, chiefly printed sources previously published in various jounals and used in the compilation of the book ca. 1977-1987 (Box 25)
    - Halflife Improvisations and Interviews, 1977-1987 TMS, with corrections ca. 1988 (Box 25)
    - Halflife Improvisations and Interviews, 1977-1987 TMS ca. 1988, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Quarter Notes Improvisations and Interviews, TMs & printed sources previously published in various journals and used in the compilation of the book ca. 1989-1994 (Box 26)
    - Translation Dante's Inferno: Translations by Twenty Contemporary Poets Canto XIII TMs & Galley 1992 Nov (Box 26)
    - Translation Motets by Eugenio Montale TMs, with corrections [1981] (Box 26)
    - Translation Orphic Songs by Dino Campana TMs ca. 1984 (Box 26)
    - Translation The Storm and Other Things by Eugenio Montale, TMs, with heavy corrections ca. 1978 (Box 26)
    - Translation The Storm and Other Things by Eugenio Montale, TMs, with corrections ca. 1978 (Box 26)
    - Translation The Storm and Other Things by Eugenio Montale, TMs, with notations by Vinio Rossi ca. 1978 (Box 26)
    - The World of the Ten Thousand Things TMs, with corrections ca. 1990 (Box 26)
    - The World of the Ten Thousand Things Master Galleys 1990 Apr (Box 27)
    - The World of the Ten Thousand Things Author's Galleys 1990 Apr (Box 27)
    - The World of the Ten Thousand Things Page Proofs, Master Pages 1990 (Box 27)
    - Zone Journals TMs ca. 1987 (Box 27)
    - Zone Journals TMs, 9 Electrostatic Copies ca. 1987, 5 folders (Box 27-28)
    - Zone Journals TMs (Setting Copy) 1987 (Box 28)
    - Zone Journals Master Galleys, with cover sample 1987 Jun (Box 28)
    - Zone Journals Author's Galleys, with corrections 1987 Jun (Box 28)
    - Zone Journals Galleys (2 Sets) 1987 Jun (Box 28)
    - Zone Journals Page Proofs, Master Pages 1987 Aug (Box 29)
    - Zone Journals Page Proofs [1987 Aug] (Box 29)
  - C: Miscellaneous Manuscripts 1963-1998, n.d. (Box 29)
    - Brief Introductions and Discussions re Giacomo Leopardi, Larry Levis, Eugenio Montale, Charles Simic, and Peter Taylor; and notes re "Coda" ca. 1996-1998, n.d. (Box 29)
    - Contemporary Authors Autobiography Essay AMs ca. 1988 (Box 29)
    - Contemporary Authors Autobiography Essay 4 TMs ca. 1988 (Box 29)
    - Correspondences Masters Thesis submitted to the State University of Iowa 1963 Jun (Box 29)
    - Foreword to The Gatehouse Heaven: Poems by James Kimbrell & TMs [1997 Apr] (Box 29)
    - Gettysburg Review Essays 1992 & 1994 (Box 29)
    - "Poems rejected for The Grave of the Right Hand and The Dream Animal(and forever)" TMs ca. 1968-1970 (Box 29)
    - Poems--Miscellaneous ca. 1988-1998 (Box 29)
      , including: "After Rereading Robert Graves, I Go Outside to Get My Head Together," "American Twilight," "Citronella," "Disjecta Membra," "Jesuit Graves," "A Journal of One Significant Landscape," "Looking Around II," "St. Augustine and the Arctic Bear," "3 January 1993," and untitled
    - The New Yorker Poetry Galleys 1977-1991 (Box 29)
    - Poetry published in Magazines (Galleys) 1989-1997 (Box 29)
    - Questions about "A Journal of the Year of the Ox" n.d. (Box 29)
    - "Remarks at the 4th Sino-American Writer's Conference, Leshan, Sichan Province, China" 1988 Apr 12 (Box 29)
      including text from Barry Lopez
- Manuscripts by Other Authors 1974-1998, n.d. (Box 30-35)
  arranged by the name of the author
  - Gale Acuff [1994] (Box 30)
  - Ai (Florence Anthony) ca. 1979-1982 (Box 30)
  - Pam Alexander 1988 (Box 30)
  - Tom Andrews 1989 (Box 30)
  - David Berman n.d. (Box 30)
  - Don Bogen 1994 (Box 30)
  - Robert Bradley [1990] (Box 30)
  - James Brasfield 1996 (Box 30)
  - Lucie Brock-Broido, Trouble Child and A Hunger 1986-1987 (Box 30)
  - Julia Budenz, "Umbra," Chapter 1 of Umbrageous Vision1989 (Box 30)
  - Franco Buffoni 1996-1997 (Box 30)
  - Heather Burns 1994 (Box 30)
  - Stuart Calderwood 1988 (Box 30)
  - Mike Chitwood 1990 (Box 30)
  - Nicholas Christopher, Desperate Characters & Other Poems1987 (Box 30)
  - Leonard Cirino 1991 (Box 30)
  - Killarney Clary, October Play1993 (Box 30)
  - Brian Clements 1994 (Box 30)
  - Stephen Conkle 1978, 1984 (Box 30)
  - Alfred Corn, The West Door1987 (Box 31)
  - Tony Crunk, New Covenant Bound1992 (Box 31)
  - Philip Deaver 1986 (Box 31)
  - Annie Dillard, "The Land Nobody Knows [North Yemen]" [1984 Jun 8] (Box 31)
  - Robert Fagles 1983-1987 (Box 31)
  - Aaron Fischer, Hansel in Recovery1989 (Box 31)
  - Scott Ellsworth Francis 1987 (Box 31)
  - Sarah Gambito 1996 (Box 31)
  - Dana Gioia 1986-1987 (Box 31)
  - Rebecca Givens 1997 (Box 31)
  - Elton Glaser 1975-1977, 1997 (Box 31)
  - Michele Glazer, It is Hard to Look at What We Came to Think We'd Come to See1997 (Box 31)
  - Loren Graham, Mose1992 (Box 31)
  - Frank Graziano [1983] (Box 31)
  - Donald Hall, The One Day1988 (Box 31)
  - Colin Hamilton, "The Memory Palace" 1997 (Box 31)
  - Michael Hannon 1989-1993 (Box 31)
  - David Harris n.d. (Box 31)
  - Brian Henry, "Exquisite Disjunctions, Exquisite Arrangements: Jorie Graham's 'Strangeness of Strategy'" 1997 (Box 31)
  - Brenda Hillman, Death Tractates1989 (Box 31)
  - Garrett Hongo, The River of Heaven1987, n.d. (Box 31)
  - Garrett Hongo, Volcano Journal1993 (Box 32)
  - Laura Jensen, Walking Tour1994 (Box 32)
  - Donald Justice 1982-1992 (Box 32)
  - Hunter Kennedy 1997 (Box 32)
  - Kerry Shawn Keys, Bones and Buzzards1994 (Box 32)
  - Damon Krukowski, "Lyrical Misgivings," & "Poems Four to Six" [1989], n.d. (Box 32)
  - Jo Ellen Kwiatek, Eleven Days Before Spring1994 (Box 32)
  - Carolyn Lau, Wode Shuofa (My Way of Speaking)1987 & 1989 (Box 32)
  - Jon Loomis 1994-1996 (Box 32)
  - J.D. McClatchy, Scenes from Another Life& Essay re Poetry 1979, 1988 (Box 32)
  - Lynne McMahon, Faith[1986] & n.d. (Box 32)
  - J. Michael Martin 1983 (Box 32)
  - Bill Matthews 1976 (Box 32)
  - Paul Monette, Love Alone[1987] (Box 32)
  - Eugenio Montale, Collected Poetry 1926-1956, translated from Italian by Jonathan Galassi 1992, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Rochelle Nameroff, Runaway1984 (Box 33)
  - Paul Nelson, The Hard Shapes of Paradise[1987] (Box 33)
  - Marlon Ohnesonge-Fick 1985 (Box 33)
  - Sophia Orr n.d. (Box 33)
  - Eric Pankey, The Late Romances1996 (Box 33)
  - John Piller, Blossom in the Blood1994 (Box 33)
  - Don Platt, Fresh Peaches, Fireworks, & Guns1993 (Box 33)
  - Gaetano Prampolini, "Robert Lowell's Dante" n.d. (Box 33)
  - John Ridland 1996 (Box 33)
  - Rainer Maria Rilke, The Book of Fresh Beginnings, translated by David Young ca. 1994 (Box 33)
  - Maggie Ross 1992 (Box 33)
  - Peter Russell 1996 (Box 33)
  - David St. John 1979-1989 (Box 33)
  - David St. John, Terraces of Rain1987 (Box 33)
  - Rod Santos 1987-1995 (Box 34)
  - Rod Santos, The Southern Reachesca. 1989 (Box 34)
  - Nathan A. Scott, Jr. 1989 (Box 34)
  - William A. Sessions 1984 (Box 34)
  - Charles Simic 1989-1998 (Box 34)
  - Maurya Simon, The Golden Labyrinth: Poems1994 (Box 34)
  - Jeffrey Skinner 1984 (Box 34)
  - Dave Smith 1988 (Box 34)
  - Marcia Southwick 1997 (Box 34)
  - Mark Strand 1987-1993 (Box 34)
  - Mary Szybist 1994 (Box 34)
  - James Tate, Viper Jazz1974 (Box 35)
  - Richard Tillinghast 1994 (Box 35)
  - Unknown Authors n.d. (Box 35)
  - Bruce Weigl, Song of Napalm1988 (Box 35)
  - Dana White 1984 (Box 35)
  - Sam Witt n.d. (Box 35)
  - David Young 1977-1992, n.d., 2 folders (Box 35)
  - David Young, The Planet on the Desk Selected & New Poems 1960-1990[1989 Aug 16] (Box 35)
- Miscellaneous Papers ca. 1890-1998, n.d. (Box 36-38)
  - Artwork 1985, n.d. (Box 36)
  - Artwork--J.M. Martin 1992 (Box 36)
  - Artwork--Maurya Simon 1984-1997 (Box 36)
  - Artwork--Heather Spears 1988 (Box 36)
  - Artwork--David Summers n.d. (Box 36)
  - Biographical Entries 1983-1998 (Box 36)
  - Contracts & Publication Agreements 1977-1998, 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Dissertation Chapter "Charles Wright's Dora Markus" by Antonella Francini 1985 (Box 36)
  - Essay "New Son of Imagism Gone Baroque" by Peter Stitt 1986 (Box 36)
  - Essays concerning Charles Wright by Annie Finch, Mark Strand, Andrew Zawackie, David Swerdlow, David St. John, Pat Cutting, Dorothy Barresi, and David Young 1986-1997 (Box 36)
  - Essay "The Pragmatic Imagination and the Secret of Poetry" by Mark Jarman about Charles Wright, C.K. Williams, and Philip Levine, published in Gettysburg Review1988 (Box 36)
  - Essay "Charles Wright's Invention" by Stephen Coyner 1990 (Box 36)
  - Essay "A Wright-er's Landscape of the Impersonal" by Tori Rowan in The Declaration1990 Nov (Box 36)
  - Essay "Cryptography: Photography and Quotation in Charles Wright's Poetry and Poetic" by Michael Theune 1997 (Box 36)
  - Essay "Poetry and Silence at the End of the Century" by Calvin Bedient n.d. (Box 36)
  - Interview "Charles Wright on Eugene Montale and Dino Campana" by Mary Zeppa in Poet News1985 Oct (Box 36)
  - Interview "The Metaphysics of the Quotidian" A Conversation with Charles Wright edited by Earl Ingersoll and Stan Sanvel Rubin 1986 Apr 3 (Box 36)
  - Interview with Carol Ellis, published in Iowa Journal of Literary Studies1986 (Box 36)
  - Interview with Sherod Santos (1987), published in Halflife 1986-1987 (Box 37)
  - Interview--Oberlin College Creative Writing Program Guest Writer Questions 1987 (Box 37)
  - "An Interview with Charles Wright" by J.D. McClatchy, published as "The Art of Poetry XLI, Charles Wright" in The Paris Review1988 (Box 37)
  - Interview "The Impossibility of Salvation A Conversation with Poet Charles Wright" by Miriam Marty Clark 1989 Feb (Box 37)
  - Interview & Essay from the 10th Annual Literary Festival honoring Charles Wright at Emory & Henry College and published in The Iron Mountain Review1991 Oct (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous ca. 1969-1988, n.d. (Box 37)
  - News Clippings & Printed 1976-1997, n.d. (Box 37)
  - Photographs ca. 1890-1997, n.d., 2 folders (Box 37)
  - Programs for Awards, Readings, etc. ca. 1975-1998, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - Reviews-- Bloodlines 1975-1976 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- China Trace 1977-1978 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- Country Music 1984-1985 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- The Dream Animal[1968] (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- The Grave of the Right Hand1970 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- Halflife1990 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- Hard Freight 1973-1974 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- Orphic Songs by Dino Campana, translated by Charles Wright 1985 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- The Other Side of the River1984 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- The Southern Cross 1982-1983 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- The World of the Ten Thousand Things: Poems 1980-19901990 (Box 38)
  - Reviews-- Zone Journals 1987-1990 (Box 38)
  - Royalties & Honorariums ca. 1977-1997 (Box 38)
  - Slides of Artwork by David Freed and Ferrara, Italy 1985, n.d. (Box 38)
  - Student Papers re Wright's Work ca. 1976-1997 (Box 38)
  - Translation of The Other Side of the River by Charles Wright into Italian by Gaetano Prampolini 1998 (Box 38)
  - Translations of the Poetry of Charles Wright into Italian & German 1991-1995, n.d. (Box 38)
  - Virginia Writers of Distinctions: Charles Wright "Notes to Help in the Study of Charles Wright and Chickamauga" [ca. 1997] (Box 38)
  - Recording of Charles Wright, mailed to him by Professor Janet E. Dunleavy, Department of English, University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee 1973 Nov 2, Reel-to-reel tape recording (Othertype Audiotape 0001)
  - Interview of Charles Wright at Oberlin College; an edited transcript of the interview was printed in Field, no. 17, and in 1976 Nov, Cassette tape recording (Othertype Audiocassette 0017 no. 1 & no. 2)
    Part One covers from page 59-74 in Halflife
    Part Two covers from page 74-88 in Halflife
  - Interview of Charles Wright by Robert Peters at the University of California at Irvine, discussing China Trace as the completion of his trilogy of poem books 1978 Feb 2, Cassette tape recording (Othertype Audiocassette 0017 no. 3)
  - Poetry Reading by Charles Wright at the Poetry Center, SFSU, including "Homage to Paul Cezanne" and discussing and reading from China Trace1980 Apr 16, Cassette tape recording (Othertype Audiocassette 0017 no. 4)
  - Watershed Tapes Recording of Charles Wright Poetry, Side One 32:00 Minutes, Side Two 31:37 Minutes "Approval Copy" 1985, Cassette tape recording (Othertype Audiocassette 0017 no. 5)
  - Identification Pin of Charles Penzel Wright, Sr., an engineer at the United States Tennessee Valley Authority Pickwick Dam, No. 11 ca. 1935 (Box-folder Mini-Tray 45)
  - Identification Pin of Charles Penzel Wright, Jr., for the the Port Townsend Writers Conference 1984 (Box-folder Mini-Tray 45)
  - Three Wood Blocks, with the letters X, Y, and Z n.d. (Box-folder Mini-Tray 45)
  - "Berkeley 1962" Study for Charles and Holly from Carlo [1962] (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Photograph of Charles Wright by Gerard Malanga 1975 (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Pen & Ink Drawing, "Pilgrims (After Michaux)" by Charles Seluzicki for Charles Wright 1982 Dec 17 (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Four Calendars illustrated by [Elio Schneeman] 1994-1997 (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Artist's Proof "My Right Hand Aches For You" by R. Fredrikhelson 1987 Oct (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Reprint of "Walking in the Mad Space" by Elio Schneeman 1998 May 16 (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Photograph of Charles and Luke Wright n.d. (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Photograph of Charles Wright n.d. (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Prints of Charles Wright, Philip Levine, and unidentified by David Freed n.d. (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Five Prints, "Like the Old Songs," "As Love Is.. .," "The Red Clay Below Him," "That Stalk," and "Are You Here?" n.d. (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Newsclippings re Charles Wright and the winning of the Ruth Lilly Poetry Prize 1993 (Oversize OS Box P-24)
  - Dust Jackets for Appalachia, Bloodlines, Chickamauga, The Grave of the Right Hand, The Other Side of the River, and The World of the Ten Thousand Things Poems 1980-1990ca. 1970-1998 (Oversize OS Box M-22)
  - Genealogical Chart for the Winter family n.d. (Oversize OS Box M-22)
  - A Rubbing of Oriental Artwork; a man is seated in a one-horse chariot and followed by a servant with an umbrella n.d. (Box-folder OS Tray 17)